# Jacob Scott Laurel

♠ https://jsl1994.github.io/ ☐ jlaurel2@illinois.edu ☐ Google Scholar

### RESEARCH SUMMARY

My mission as a programming languages researcher is to build automated and mathematically principled program analyses for continuous computations. My efforts focus on two popular paradigms that expose continuous computations: differentiable and probabilistic programming languages. While a programming languages viewpoint anchors my research, my work spans the full computing stack: from applying formal methods to prove properties about differentiable programs all the way down to building compilers to generate fast inference code on embedded systems.

# **EDUCATION**

Aug. 2017 - present

Ph.D. in Computer Science

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Advisor: Sasa Misailovic

Research areas: Differentiable and Probabilistic Programming Languages, Abstract Interpretation,

Program Analysis, Formal Methods, Compilers, Embedded Systems

Aug. 2012 - May 2017

**B.S.** E.E in Electrical Engineering Summa Cum Laude UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA AT BIRMINGHAM **B.S.** in Mathematics (Applied Mathematics and Scientific Computation Track) Summa Cum Laude GPA: 3.95/4.0

# WORK EXPERIENCE

July 2018 – Present

Research Assistant

University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Advisor: Sasa Misailovic

May 2019 – Aug. 2019

Ph.D. Research Intern

NASA Langley Research Center

Mentors: Cesar Muñoz and Aaron Dutle

Applied program analysis to quantify floating point error in probabilistic programs.

May 2016 - Aug. 2016

Undergraduate Research Intern

University of Central Florida

Helped develop a novel video summarization technique using LSTM Deep Neural Networks. Work published in CVPR 2017.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE AND JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- Jacob Laurel, Siyuan Brant Qian, Gagandeep Singh, Sasa Misailovic. Synthesizing Precise Static Analyzers for Automatic Differentiation. In Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages, and Applications (OOPSLA 2023). Acceptance rate: 36%.
- 2. Rem Yang, Jacob Laurel, Sasa Misailovic, Gagandeep Singh. Provable Defense Against Geometric Transformations. In 11th International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR 2023). Acceptance rate: 31%. Designated notable, top 25% of papers.
- 3. Vimuth Fernando, Keyur Joshi, **Jacob Laurel**, Sasa Misailovic. Dynamic Monitoring of Uncertainty for Distributed Asynchronous Programs with Diamont. In *International Journal on Software Tools for Technology Transfer* (STTT 2023).
- 4. Ashitabh Misra, **Jacob Laurel**, Sasa Misailovic. ViX: Analysis-driven Compiler for Efficient Low-Precision Differentiable Inference. In *Design Automation and Test in Europe* (**DATE 2023**). Full Paper Acceptance rate: 25%.

Jacob Scott Laurel Curriculum Vitæ

5. Jacob Laurel, Rem Yang, Shubham Ugare, Robert Nagel, Gagandeep Singh, Sasa Misailovic. A General Construction for Abstract Interpretation of Higher-Order Automatic Differentiation. In Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages, and Applications (OOPSLA 2022). Acceptance rate: 31%.

- 6. Jacob Laurel, Rem Yang, Gagandeep Singh, Sasa Misailovic. A Dual Number Abstraction for Static Analysis of Clarke Jacobians. In Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages (POPL 2022). Acceptance rate: 23%.
- 7. Vimuth Fernando, Keyur Joshi, Jacob Laurel, Sasa Misailovic. Diamont: Dynamic Monitoring of Uncertainty for Distributed Asynchronous Programs. In 21st International Conference on Runtime Verification (RV 2021). Acceptance rate: 38%.
- 8. Jacob Laurel, Rem Yang, Atharva Sehgal, Shubham Ugare, Sasa Misailovic. Statheros: A Compiler for Efficient Low-Precision Probabilistic Programming. In 58th Design Automation Conference (DAC 2021). Acceptance rate: 23%.
- 9. Jacob Laurel, Sasa Misailovic. Continualization of Probabilistic Programs with Correction. In 29<sup>th</sup> European Symposium on Programming (ESOP 2020). Acceptance rate: 31%.
- 10. Aidean Sharghi, Jacob Laurel, Boqing Gong. Query-Focused Video Summarization: Dataset, Evaluation, and A Memory Network Based Approach. In Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR 2017). Acceptance rate: 29%.

#### **PREPRINTS**

11. Zixin Huang, Jacob Laurel, Saikat Dutta, Sasa Misailovic. Precise Abstract Interpretation of Probabilistic Programs with Interval Data Uncertainty. Under Submission

#### POSTERS AND WORKSHOP PAPERS

- 12. Jacob Laurel, Siyuan Brant Qian, Gagandeep Singh, Sasa Misailovic. Abstract Interpretation for Automatic Differentiation. In Languages for Inference Workshop (LAFI 2024).
- 13. Jacob Laurel. Exact Quantification of Continuity Correction Error in Probabilistic Programs. Poster presented at 1st International Conference on Probabilistic Programming (PROBPROG 2018).

# Honors and Awards

One of 6 UIUC students selected to attend the Global Young Scientists Summit in Singapore (GYSS 2024)

UIUC Mavis Future Faculty Fellowship (\$ 2000 Award)

UIUC CS Department Outstanding Graduate Student Ambassador (\$ 100 Award)

UIUC ALERT Program Mentor Award (\$ 1000 Award)

UIUC Sloan UCEM Scholarship (\$ 40,000 Award) 2017-Present

UAB Presidential Honors List for 4.0 GPA during semester

UAB Presidential Scholarship as National Hispanic Recognition Program Scholar

UAB School of Engineering Dupuis Scholarship

UAB School of Engineering Undergraduate Research Award for Honors Research

Inducted into Tau Beta Pi Engineering Honor Society

#### RESEARCH TALKS AND PRESENTATIONS

Invited Talk: "Automated Analyses for Continuous Computations" - Columbia University Systems Seminar (host: Baishakhi Ray)

Invited Talk: "Abstractly Interpreting Differentiable Programming" - Purdue University PurPL

Seminar (host: Ben Delaware)

Invited Talk: "Abstractly Interpreting Differentiable Programming" - University of Michigan

Midwest Programming Languages Summit 2023 Oct. 2023

Jan. 2024

Dec. 2023

2023 2023-2024

2023

2023

2012-2017

2012-2016 2015

2015 2013

Jacob Scott Laurel Curriculum Vitæ

Invited Talk: "Abstractly Interpreting Differentiable Programming - A Trilogy" - Cornell

Oct. 2023 University PLDG Seminar (host: Adrian Sampson)

Invited Talk: "Abstractly Interpreting Differentiable Programming" - Argonne National

Aug. 2023 Laboratory CS Seminar (host: Jan Hückelheim)

Invited Talk: "A General Construction for Abstract Interpretation of Higher-Order Automatic

Differentiation" - UCF CRCV Seminar (host: Niels Da Vitoria Lobo)

Invited Talk: "Abstract Interpretation for Differentiable Programming" - UC Berkeley Formal

Methods Seminar (host: Sanjit Seshia)

Invited Talk: "Abstract Interpretation for Differentiable Programming" - Stanford Software

June 2022 Seminar (host: Clark Barrett)

June 2023

July 2022

## RESEARCH MENTORING

Mentored two graduate students and five undergraduate students:

Feb. 2020 - May 2023 Rem Yang (BS, UIUC) - Co-author on DAC21, POPL22, OOPSLA22, ICLR23

Mar. 2020 - May 2021 Atharva Sehgal (BS, UIUC) - Co-author on DAC21

May. 2021 - May 2023 Robert Nagel (BS, UIUC) - Co-author on OOPSLA22

Nov. 2020 - Aug. 2022 Shubham Ugare (PhD, UIUC) - Co-author on DAC21, OOPSLA22

May. 2022 - Feb. 2023 Ashitabh Misra (PhD, UIUC) - Co-author on DATE23

Jan. 2023 - present Siyuan Brant Qian (BS, UIUC/ZJU) - Co-author on OOPSLA23, LAFI24 May 2023 - Aug. 2023 Jonah Black (BS UIUC) - Mentored through the UIUC ALERT Program

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Spring 2023 UIUC CS 477 Formal Software Development Methods (Guest Lecture)
Fall 2019 UIUC CS 421 Programming Languages and Compilers (Teaching Assistant)

Spring 2019 UIUC CS 126 Software Design Studio (Teaching Assistant)
Fall 2018 UIUC CS 173 Discrete Structures (Teaching Assistant)

Spring 2018 UIUC CS 374 Algorithms and Models of Computation (Teaching Assistant)

Spring 2014 UAB ECE 312 Electrical Systems (Undergraduate Course Assistant)

#### OPEN-SOURCE SOFTWARE CONTRIBUTIONS

I have led the development of the following open-source software libraries:

**AbstractAD**: AbstractAD is a parametric abstract interpretation of higher-order differentiable programs that allows for expressive abstract domains (like Zonotopes), published in OOPSLA22.

It is available at https://github.com/uiuc-arc/AbstractAD

DeepJ: DeepJ is a sound abstract interpretation of Clarke Generalized Jacobians, published in

POPL<sub>22</sub>. It is available at https://github.com/uiuc-arc/DeepJ

Statheros: Statheros is a compiler for fixed-point probabilistic programming, published in DAC21.

It is available at https://github.com/uiuc-arc/Statheros

**Pasado**: Pasado is a tool for synthesizing static analyzers for Automatic Differentiation, published in OOPSLA23. It is available at https://github.com/uiuc-arc/Pasado as well as

https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8332724

#### EXPERIENCE WITH RESEARCH GRANTS

Assisted Sasa Misailovic and Gagandeep Singh in the preparation of the following research grant applications:

Static Analysis of Gradients for Building Trustworthy AI Systems - NSF CCF SHF:Medium grant application

# SERVICE

Fall 2023

Fall 2023 Graduate Student Representative for UIUC Faculty Awards Committee

Jacob Scott Laurel Curriculum Vitæ

Summer 2023 Reviewer - WFVML 2023

Summer 2023 Mentor for UIUC Accelerated Learning and Engineering Research Training (ALERT) Program

Mar. 2023 Graduate Ambassador and Panelist for session on Diversity and Inclusivity for UIUC CS Visit Day

Fall 2022 - Spring 2023 Graduate Student Representative for UIUC's CS Graduate Study Committee

Summer 2022 Reviewer - ECCV 2022

Jan. 2020

Summer 2022 Artifact Evaluation Committee - SAS 2022

Fall 2021 Panelist for UIUC's Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers Graduate Student Panel

Summer 2021 Artifact Evaluation Committee - OOPSLA 2021 Mar. 2020 Graduate Ambassador for UIUC CS Visit Day

Graduate Volunteer for UIUC School of Engineering Undergraduate Research Expo

Fall 2019 Organizer - UIUC Brett Daniel Software Engineering Seminar

#### References

#### Sasa Misailovic (advisor)

Associate Professor

Department of Computer Science

https://misailo.cs.illinois.edu/

misailo@illinois.edu

#### Gagandeep Singh

Assistant Professor

Department of Computer Science https://ggndpsngh.github.io/

ggnds@illinois.edu

#### Darko Marinov

Professor

Department of Computer Science

https://mir.cs.illinois.edu/marinov/

marinov@illinois.edu

# Sayan Mitra

Professor

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering

https://mitras.ece.illinois.edu/

mitras@illinois.edu